<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY RFC7480 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7480.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC7483 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7483.xml'>
<!ENTITY domain_check.json PUBLIC '' 'domain_check.json' >
<!ENTITY variant_domain.json PUBLIC '' 'variant_domain.json' >
]>
<?rfc toc="true"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-newton-regext-rdap-domain-availability-00" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="RDAP Domain Availability">Using RDAP as a Domain Availability Service</title>
        <author fullname="Andrew Lee Newton" initials="A.L." surname="Newton">
            <organization abbrev="ARIN">American Registry for Internet Numbers</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>PO Box 232290</street>
                    <city>Centreville</city>
                    <region>VA</region>
                    <country>US</country>
                    <code>20120</code>
                </postal>
                <email>andy@arin.net</email>
                <uri>http://www.arin.net</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Marcos Sanz" initials="M." surname="Sanz">
            <organization abbrev="DENIC eG">DENIC eG</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Kaiserstraße 75 - 77</street>
                    <code>60329</code>
                    <city>Frankfurt am Main</city>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <email>sanz@denic.de</email>
                <uri>https://www.denic.de</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document describes a minimal profile of RDAP which can be used to check
                the availability of domain names available for registration.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                While RDAP <xref target="RFC7480"></xref> has all the necessary properties to serve the information necessary
                to determine if a domain name is available for registration, without proper signalling
                an RDAP server is likely to return more information than is required to fulfill this
                requirement, thus wasting bandwidth and server resources, and may return negative answers when positive answers 
                are more appropriate.
            </t>            
            <t>
                This document defines HTTP query parameters to be used by clients to signal the
                intent of the query is for an availability check. Servers may then respond with
                a much smaller and less costly payload than they would have otherwise. The contents
                of the payload would be at the discretion of the policies of the server operator within
                the guidelines of RDAP responses <xref target="RFC7483"></xref>.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Query Parameter" anchor="query_parameter">
            <t>
                To signal that the client is only interested in domain availability checking,
                the client MUST use the query parameter 'availabilityCheck' in the RDAP query for
                a domain with value '1'. This query parameter has no meaning for other RDAP queries, and therefore
                should be ignored in those cases.
            </t>
            <figure align="center" title="Example RDAP Query" anchor="example_query">
                <preamble>The following is an example RDAP query for a domain availability check.</preamble>
                <artwork xml:space="preserve" align="center">https://example.com/rdap/domain/example.com?availabilityCheck=1</artwork>
            </figure>
            <figure align="center" title="Example RDAP Response" anchor="domain_check.json">
                <preamble>The following is an example response.</preamble>
                <artwork xml:space="preserve" align="center">&domain_check.json;
                </artwork>
                <postamble>This response, not including the HTTP headers, is 174 octets long.</postamble>
            </figure>
            <t>
                When this query parameter is given, servers MUST reply with HTTP return codes as specified
                in <xref target="answers"></xref>.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Positive and Negative Answers" anchor="answers">
            <t>
                RDAP <xref target="RFC7480"></xref> provides guidance on using HTTP return codes more
                contextual for the lookup of domain registration information than domain availability information.
                A query for domain registration information should result in a negative answer (e.g. 404 NOT FOUND) if
                the name is not registered (or not in active use or in another state where it may be considered to
                have a unregistration according to policy). However, a query for domain availability information
                upon the same domain name should yield a positive answer if the domain is available for registration
                within the bounds of the registry policy.
                In other words, the return codes may vary given the appropriate context.
            </t>
            <t>
                In the context of domain availability, RDAP servers should return positive answers (in accordance with
                server policies for rate limiting and access control) if the domain
                registry for which the RDAP server is responding allows registration of the queried domain even
                if the domain is currently registered at the time of the query. For example, an RDAP server answering for foo.example
                would return a positive answer (i.e. 200 OK) for fiz.foo.example if the domain status was active or inactive,
                but it would return a negative answer for buzz.bar.example because it is not the registry for bar.example.
            </t>
            <figure align="center" title="Example Positive Answer" anchor="variant_domain.json">
                <preamble>The example in <xref target="domain_check.json"></xref> shows a positive answer for
                a domain that is inactive (i.e. not registered). This example shows a positive answer for
                a domain that is active, including variants and the expiration date.</preamble>
                <artwork xml:space="preserve" align="center">&variant_domain.json;
                </artwork>
                <postamble>This response, not including the HTTP headers, is 908 octets long in UTF-8 encoding.</postamble>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section title="Availability Information Query" anchor="availability_query">
            <t>
                All of the examples given in this document have been reduced from examples in <xref target="RFC7483"></xref>,
                demonstrating that domain availability information is a subset of domain registration information in the
                RDAP data model.
                Some clients may desire both domain registration information and domain availability information.
                To signal that the client is interested in both contexts,
                the client MUST use the query parameter 'availabilityInformation' in the RDAP query for
                a domain with value '1'. This query parameter has no meaning for other RDAP queries, and therefore
                should be ignored in those cases.
            </t>
            <t>
                Servers MUST respond with positive answers as specified in <xref target="answers"></xref>, but
                SHOULD NOT redact other registration information (i.e. entities, name servers, etc...) in accordance
                with their access policies.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="RDAP Conformance">
            <t>
                Servers MUST include "domain_check_0" in the rdapConformance array of their response when
                modifying their behavior according to this specification. That is, this value should only
                be placed in the array when responding to a query with one of the query parameters in
                <xref target="query_parameter"></xref> or <xref target="availability_query"></xref>.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            
            &RFC7480;
            &RFC7483;
            
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
